for me when when you talk about
non-theism
it's almost like the question of the
objective existence of god is just the
wrong question
yes i the the core of the non-theist
position
is rejecting the shared so it rejects
the shared presuppositions
of both the theists and the atheists
about how to best understand
this phenomena that you and i are
clearly exists
which is the experience of the sacred
that is really transformative of people
so right and what i think is the idea
that you know
um trying to make trying to frame this
in terms of the existence or
non-existence of
a being and that it's primarily uh
that and that the way we understand that
is by
manipulating beliefs and that we
can sort of nail down uh get some final
answer about the most
appropriate symbols for that these are
all things
right and so the theater says yes to all
of those and the atheist
agrees that that's the right framing and
then says no to all of those
and the non-theist says no i reject that
framing
that framing is i think actually miss
the phenomena um and the
meaning that is afforded by the you know
the connectedness
that the phenomena is is pointing to so
the non-theist yeah rejects that
question
the non-theist says can we come up with
a framing that puts uh that well i once
described this to you
that affords us to fall deeply in love
with being
once again this is very like that's a
nichian thing almost right
it's it's it's niching in some way but i
think it's heideggerian
because i mean i think the problem i
mean this is a
critique that he uh heidiger made of
nietzsche that nietzsche basically
is still locked into nietzsche basically
inverts christianity
so he's still locked to it so i think
the atheist just
inverts theism and they're still locked
to it and i want to break out of it
it's kind of like the the white
supremacy versus white oppression
narrative right it's like the first way
that you
a narrative that doesn't serve the first
the first response to it is just its
inverse yes exactly and you have to try
and break
past them which is what you were trying
to talk about with your example of
parkour
that neither the white supremacy or the
white oppression
model explains what actually emerged and
was created in that situation
yeah by these kids who yeah from
you know yeah and you know and they had
an agency
they created this yeah yeah and uh
and it works it works as a tool
to to bridge right
and i think that um i think that in some
ways like uh
it's you can almost view parkour as a
kind of analogy or
a potential precursor to how can we
build these tools
that function it's like i um
you know god doesn't whether god exists
in a sort of
external metaphysical objective sense
it kind of doesn't matter because the
representation of god
or the meaningfulness of those things
has to exist for us on some level
yes um and if we're not addressing that
and if we can't address it in a way that
can invite in the believers and the
non-believers
um then
then we're just stuck with war i guess
yeah
but that's why i think what's that's why
i'm so attracted to your project because
you know um as much as i love and
respect what peterson's done he kind of
flirts at the edge of saying it's
neither
yeah yeah he rejects the atheism and he
describes christianity in such a way
that it'd be very easy to be
non-theistic but he doesn't go to the
point of saying
i'm actually approaching this as a
non-theist yeah
and i've as you know i've criticized him
for yeah
not doing that because i think you can
make a very clear case that
uh that young is a non-theist for
example um
yeah so yeah so
that i mean i've been you know i've been
trying to articulate this with this
notion of transactivity
and and the notion of this is
extraordinarily valuable like that just
blew my mind when i first
encountered the idea of transactivity
that you know there's the object
there's the observer of the object and
then there's the relationship yeah right
and that so much of where we get stuck
[Music]
is reframed once you recognize that the
there's a reality within the
relationship
yeah well that's exactly and you know
and i think
i i i you know i've been helped by
people like corban
and and the imaginal as not the
subjective image or just the objective
thing but
as the enacted image schema that
actually allows us to afford
you know uh fine transactivity find that
connectedness
and i see a lot of like i i see a lot of
what you're doing in parkour
is exactly that kind of enacted imaginal
work
imaginal play i should say
the whole point about the metaphor we
can't
we can't win by playing the game that's
right
my way of trying to understand what it
is to not play their game
and to shift over to in a totally
different game to shift the culture